so the real idea of this video is to set
you on the right path to getting good at
piano to give you an overview of some
important beginning steps and to set you
up to keep learning most effectively so
most of these steps are the start of
some ongoing things that you're always
going to be improving upon music is
something that you learn incrementally
and slowly where you constantly build
upon something else that you know so
it's crucial to start approaching it in
the right way now if you want to get
better as quick as you can think of it
like a language you start learning a few
phrases then you can string a sentence
together eventually you can become
fluent not everyone's going to be
shakespeare but you can get to a point
where you can say what you want to say
if you learn it right
every topic i discuss here deserves its
own in-depth video and we'll get one if
there's not one up already so here i'm
just gonna really touch upon each topic
and why it's important as there's not
time to unpack everything completely in
one video but it's important to have a
nice clear organized overview of
everything that you should be looking
into and practicing these things will
help you play a much better long game
and become a musician with a much higher
level of freedom on the piano and by
that i mean someone who could work out
something by ear that's in their head or
that someone else has played write a
song see a set of chords and just be
able to play them in different ways
different styles change your part to
make it your own improvise learn new
music much quicker and be able to
memorize much more of it pick up new
techniques and improve quicker basically
become someone who could just sit down
at the piano and be able to play
something as opposed to someone who
might know a couple of songs or could
read a bit of sheet music okay but if
you take that away from them they just
wouldn't know what to do with the
instrument and that's fine if that's all
you want to do this is just something
that's going to help put you on a path
to be able to do a bit more it's the
difference between learning a few
phrases and actually speaking a language
there's a mixture of practical and
theory type stuff in here but don't let
the theory put you off theory's really
just labeling things and putting a name
to it so you can find it again when you
need it when something sounds good you
need to know what it is what it's called
how it works and then with enough
experience you learn how and when to use
it that was a huge part of my learning
process i'd hear other players do things
and i was desperate to find out how they
made that sound that drive to want to
discover new sounds and new things on
the piano will take you a long way
there's obviously going to be some more
things i haven't been able to include on
this list so let me know in the comments
if there's anything else that you can
think of that's going to be really
important for beginners to learn some of
the things on this list i didn't learn
enough of early on because no one told
me to and i really wish they had because
when i did the difference it made was
massive so now i plant these seeds early
on with all my students and when they've
been playing long enough and if they
practice the results are obvious when
all this stuff links together and now
they're in a really good position to
potentially become a great musician so
there's quite a lot of stuff on this
list but don't think you have to learn
everything straight away it will take
quite a long time for some of these
things to become more of a natural part
of your musical vocab but the important
thing to take from the video is that
these are things that you need to be
working towards over time the more
internalized they are and the easier
they become the more freedom you're
going to unlock learning to play well is
much more about practice and patience
and experience and passion for music
than it is about talent
so with everything on this list i'm
going to talk a bit more about why it's
important and what it can do for you
rather than get into too much detail
about how it works and how to learn it
because like i said i'm going to do
separate videos for each of these topics
on that so probably the best thing to do
first is to get as familiar as you can
with the keyboard so the keyboard is
this part of the piano and it's still
called a keyboard even on a real piano
sometimes people overlook quite how
important this is so they learn the note
names but they don't really understand
how everything works properly and work
on it till it's at a point where it's
completely fluent when you get to that
point it makes everything else that you
learn much easier and quicker because
you always have to find note names
before starting a chord or a scale or
starting a song it can really slow down
your progress if you keep pausing and
stuttering every time you need to find a
note and you always need to find notes
so on a full size piano we have 88 keys
this one's a bit shorter it's only 73
but the word key really only means the
button that plays the note
so we have 12 different notes and then
we have higher and lower versions of
those notes so this is the high end this
is the low end so if i play these notes
and then i play
the notes that look exactly the same but
starting from here
you can hear it sounds like the same
thing but higher up and if i do it here
it sounds like the same thing but lower
down
so there's 12 different notes there's
seven white and there's five black
we start with naming the white notes
first
we use the letters a to g we tend to
find c first for now just think because
it's easier to find an a there's a few
other reasons which will become clearer
later on so if you look at the block of
two black notes go to the note that's on
the left
that's a c then we just go through in
alphabetical order c
d
e
f g
we've run out of letters that we use so
we start again at a a
b
and then it's a c again because this one
is also left of the block of two it
looks just like that one did the black
notes can have two names something flat
or something sharp so before we get
right into that there's one word you
need to know and that's semitone or half
step as a lot of people say actually
they both mean exactly the same thing so
if we take these notes
and we play them in order
these notes are all in a completely
straight line next to each other if you
look at the inside of a real piano you
can see exactly what i'm talking about
so a semitone is one note right next
door to another note so the word flat
means go one semitone down when naming
the notes and the word sharp means go
one semitone up so if i take d and
flatten it
i can call that d flat
e
e flat
g flat
a flat
b flat
if i take c and sharpen it i can call
that c sharp
d sharp
f sharp g sharp and a sharp
now i've obviously just run over that
really quickly but i've already got
videos out on how to name the white and
the black notes which go a lot more in
depth on how to learn and practice it so
to start with you just want to learn how
to name the black notes either way and
not when to use which one that'll become
clearer once you learn a few more things
once you get really familiar with the
keyboard and you can name a note without
even having to really think about it
you've put yourself in a much better
position to learn everything else much
more quickly and easily
so technique is something that you'll
always be working on there's always new
things to learn and different things you
can do for different situations but it's
important to get some of the basics down
to start with getting the technique
right can help you so much sometimes
just a really small adjustment to
something can be the difference between
fumbling apart and being able to play it
perfectly it can help you control your
touch on the piano and therefore be a
lot more musical with what you play but
also it can stop you getting injured one
of the things that piano players are
always trying to do is to get rid of
tension in their playing and that allows
you to move around a lot more
comfortably so that's mainly for your
wrists and fingers but also quite
important is for your arms and the rest
of your body and shoulders and
everything when you get started thinking
about this stuff there's actually quite
a lot to bear in mind so at the
beginning it's more about trying to
force good habits upon yourself rather
than bad habits it'll take a good while
for you to be able to do all this stuff
together automatically so they're
feeling natural and you just do them
straight away without thinking about it
but when you're practicing on your own
you just have to be really sharp and
notice what you're doing and what you're
not doing that you should be this is
where a good teacher can help because
they might notice things that you're
doing wrong that you haven't even
realized then you can correct it so
here's some of the most important things
i think you should bear in mind
sitting position people often always
tuck in far too close to the piano which
really restricts your arm movement so
pull the stool a bit further back so
your arms can reach out about this far
don't sit right back on the stall sit
more towards the front edge make sure
the stool is at the right height not too
high or too low when you're sitting up
straight on the stall pulling yourself
up from your core when your arms are
relaxed but at this angle your elbow
should be just above the keyboard height
get your feet planted flat and firmly on
the floor about shoulder width apart
that way you've got good support for the
rest of your body and you can balance
when you move about so when you're
playing arms should always want to feel
like they're holding themselves up using
the bigger muscles that way your wrists
and your fingers are free to relax and
you've got as much mobility as possible
make sure that you're not sticking
elbows out so your basic hand position
wants to look something like this you
want to form this arch going from your
wrist down your fingers to the keys if
you let your arm just hang down like
this and completely relax it
automatically forms that shape and
that's what we want at the piano make
sure fingers don't curve too much that
they don't go too flat that your wrist
isn't too high or too low sometimes
people drop it right under the keys
which most of the time is not what you
want to do that helps you touch the keys
with just the right part of your
fingertips putting all that together
with making sure that your arms feel
like they're holding themselves up and
almost craning your hand over the keys
really helps with the next part a lot of
time people think playing is all in the
fingers and finger strength but it's not
really the case it's more like the
fingers are directing the weight through
to the keys so your fingers don't want
to be doing this
make sure you're controlling the weight
of your arm so you can drop it down just
enough through your finger onto the key
let your fingertips grip the key and
allow your wrist to completely relax so
you've got maximum mobility and can move
around into whatever position you need
again let your arm and the bigger
muscles take the weight and control the
movement so another important part of
technique is knowing about finger
numbers and how to use your fingers
cleverly we number thumbs one and then
go outwards two three four five when we
play a lot of the time we think in
finger blocks so we have a block of
fingers on a certain group of notes at
one time and then for the next part of
the song we might move our hand position
to another finger block and do whatever
we need to do in that position and that
allows us to break things down into more
manageable chunks so we don't get our
fingers mixed up when we're playing and
helps us move our hand around smoothly
throughout the music to start getting
used to how to use your fingers you just
want to stick in one finger block with
all five fingers one two three four five
one for each note most of the time you
don't want to skip fingers so you don't
want to go finger one to finger three
for example leaving finger two out when
those two notes are next door to each
other so you can start and see just
because it's gonna sound good and one
basic exercise you can do is literally
just to go up and down the notes
so what you're getting used to here is
being able to control your wrist and the
weight directing through each key try
and get your way on top of each finger
that you push it's just a really small
little movement get your way over the
top of each note so what we're after is
not mushing notes together
like that and causing tension in your
wrist so after each key wrist comes up a
little bit relax it and then it can
firm up as much as it needs to just to
get into the next one but when i say
firm i don't mean tense just firm enough
so your finger doesn't your hand doesn't
completely collapse so make sure to
practice that with both hands separately
at first on your left hand you might
want to start with finger five and go
upwards instead of down
obviously there's a lot more you can do
to get that going to start with that's
just one thing to use as an example for
this video remember it's not really
about finger strength it's about
training your mind to control your
fingers and your wrists and your arms in
a way that it's not used to yet you have
to just be a bit patient with it because
it takes a lot of repetition till it
starts feeling easy imagine a kid
learning to walk for the first time is
going to be really wobbly for ages and
they're going to keep falling over but
with enough time and practice and
forcing good habits you're just able to
control it a lot more and the more you
can control it the more you can control
how the music sounds
so personally i think the best way to
think about what a scale is is a
selection of notes or colors or flavors
that we can use to make music with
there's different types of scales and
each one has a different character so
think of them as different color
palettes you can play with you can
create an infinite amount of things with
each of them but it's going to have an
overall flavor of that scale like a dark
color palette will produce a dark
picture and a bright color palette would
produce a bright picture so for example
in music we have something called the
major scale
which is kind of a bright sound versus a
minor scale
[Music]
which is a darker sound for each type of
scale there's actually 12 versions of
them one starting from each of the 12
different notes that i talked about
before
the note you start from is the home
sound in a scale number one or the root
so if i play that scale again up and
down
[Music]
it sounds finished on that note it
sounds at rest so the name of the scale
that you're playing is the name of the
note that you start from plus the scale
type so for example that was c major and
the other one i played before the darker
one was c minor they both started on c
but they were different kinds of scales
so the most useful scale to learn first
in all 12 keys is the major scale it's
the most common one and you can use this
to help you learn the minor scales
afterwards so do these ones first
there's lots of really important reasons
to learn scales inside out and it's not
just so you can pass a grade one really
important reason to learn scales is that
you're learning where the notes are for
a song that you might be playing out of
these notes you can get melodies and
chords and entire songs so you need to
be able to move through them comfortably
and i mean technically and actually
knowing where your fingers are going to
go in c that would be quite easy because
it's just all the white notes but a lot
of the scales are a mixture of white and
black notes so you have to learn where
everything is so you don't get mixed up
the next thing i don't really hear get
talked about often enough and that's
actually getting used to the sound of a
scale music is sound at the end of the
day so as musicians we need to
understand what sounds you can make and
how to make them getting used to scales
can clear up in your mind and organize
how something in music is working when
you're playing you should try and get
used to and take notice of where in a
scale anything is happening at any given
moment for example i just said the first
note of the scale sounds like home it
sounds at rest so if i play a melody
it sounds finished but if i do this
i've hung on on the second note of the
scale so it sounds like it's got
somewhere else to go the more familiar
you are with this the more you'll be
able to hear how music is actually
working you'll be able to work stuff out
by ear quicker and you'll be able to do
more things with it yourself so the next
thing following on from something i
mentioned in the technique bit you learn
how to use your fingers really cleverly
using finger blocks so for example when
i played that c scale we've got seven
different notes
and then we play this one again so i'm
obviously i haven't got seven fingers on
one hand so i need to divide
this scale up into finger blocks like
that
and that basic principle and how you can
do that in the different kinds of shapes
that different scales make is going to
teach you how to start using your
fingers cleverly which you end up
actually using in songs not just four
scales but more than that the different
shapes different scales make means that
you end up having to hold your wrist in
slightly different ways and touch the
keys in different ways and there's loads
of other little things like that which
you learn from doing them and gain
control over the keyboard remember the
more control you have the more you can
play and the more musical you can be
scales plus other exercises as well are
a really good chance to focus on your
technique when you're learning new songs
although you should also be thinking
about technique then it can be hard
sometimes because you're just trying to
memorize something or think about lots
of other things at the same time so it's
good to isolate stuff with scales you
can really focus on the things i
mentioned earlier like your sitting
position and your hand position you can
work on your control your speed you can
play scales in different ways for
different sorts of touches on the piano
like smooth playing
which is called legato and then
staccato which is
different kind of touches that you use
for different musical situations you can
work on loud and soft playing and lots
of other things as well
scales themselves aren't music but if
you use them in the right way it gives
you a lot more musical possibility don't
practice them all the time or get
obsessed with them just use them for
what you need it's also worth mentioning
that songs don't exclusively stick in
one scale all the time they sometimes
dip out or change scale but there's
often a strong backbone of one
particular scale which can make your
life a lot easier to learn things and
understand what's going on and speak the
language of music
melody is one of the most important
elements of a lot of music it's often
the most identifiable part of a song
when you have multiple versions of the
same song everything else can change but
the melody is often not always close to
or exactly the same and that's what can
make it sound like that particular song
the most coming back to the idea of
language i like to think of melody as
kind of like a musical sentence when
you're learning pay attention to the
importance of the melody learn lots of
different melodies think about the scale
it's in whether it sticks inside the
scale the whole time where in the scale
the melody is taking place at all times
and use that to familiarize yourself
with what you can do with different
notes of the scale like for example
earlier when i mentioned the root note
sounds like home and a rest look for
patterns in melodies that can help you
learn them sometimes things might repeat
like for example something like
this consistencies in songs that use
similar things with melodies to create
similar effects different styles often
have certain characteristics of what
they do with melody and if you pay
attention to it and analyze it you make
the most of your time and experience
learning this is all different aspects
of musical language that's been built up
over generations and if you're always
trying to learn more about how it works
at a deeper level you're going to be
able to speak that language much better
chords and harmony are essentially
mixing notes together in different ways
to create new and interesting sounds if
you think of notes as individual flavors
or colors different combinations of
those notes and then how those notes are
spread out and played across the piano
are going to create new mixtures of
sound there's all different kinds of
chords and harmonies you can make each
with different characters and emotional
flavors
[Music]
whether you're using more sophisticated
chords or more simple ones when you play
a chord progression which is just a
series of chords in a row it creates
movement and structure to a piece of
[Music]
music and it can also make a melody feel
completely different just as a quick
example if i take a really simple melody
and put a few different chords
underneath it it's going to sound
completely different each time
[Music]
for a much better and more in-depth
example of that from a master you should
watch jacob collier's video he did with
wired i'll link to that in the
description below it's called five
levels of harmony in order to work
towards a place where you can gain much
more control over harmony for beginners
the first thing you need to do is learn
all your major and minor chords but not
only that you need to focus on how
they're built which i'm not going to get
into too deep in this video learning how
they're built properly will help you
expand into the more colorful complex
harmonic places in the future it's also
just going to help you memorize them and
find your way around the keyboard easier
each type of chord like the scales
actually has 12 versions one starting
from each of the 12 different notes
again and also like the scales they're
named after the note you start from and
then the chord type for example c major
or g minor
these basic chords are called triads
because they've got three notes in and
just like the note names it's really
really worth learning to get these off
by heart because you're going to be
using them all the time in songs and
being able to find your way around the
keyboard playing chords easier is going
to help you learn more and more quickly
one of the challenges with piano is that
different chords even though they're the
same chords they look like different
shapes which is why we have to put extra
attention into it to get used to it so
for example a c major is a white note a
d major it's the same kind of chord but
it's got white black white and e flat
major
is black white black and all of those
require different kinds of hand
positions that you need to get used to
as well as actually just being able to
see them clearly the method i like to
use for learning instead of actually
learning all 12 majors and then all 12
minors which is 24 things to learn you
can learn all 12 majors and then one
trick to changing all of those chords to
minor so that's 12 things plus one trick
instead of 24 things so for example if
we take c major
the trick is without getting into too
much theory at this stage if you take
the middle note and put it down by one
semitone
now that's a c minor you've changed one
of the flavors in the harmony so if i
did that with a d major i just showed
you that was a d major
take the middle one put it down a
semitone
now you've got d minor the shapes are
going to look different
but it's the same chord
now i understand that's really strange
that they look different but they are
actually the same thing it's to do with
the size of the gaps between the notes
and if you saw the inside of a real
piano the size of the gaps would look
exactly the same remember the buttons
are laid out weirdly now don't worry if
you don't completely understand that
just yet there's another subject to get
first before you can really get that and
when you learn that and watch my proper
in-depth chord video at some point soon
it will be much more clear so using that
method each new trick you learn to
create a new chord type you're actually
getting 12 new chords instead of having
to learn 12 new things every time so
learning properly how the chords are
built is also going to help with that
being able to handle a lot more
information so you'll be using these
chord positions as a starting point to
create patterns breaking the notes up
rearranging the order of the notes
adding notes on moving in and out of the
notes and you can use those shapes to
help you learn much more efficiently so
you need to have the fundamental way of
playing a chord down to make everything
else much easier in the future they
allow you to learn much more quickly
because you're processing less
information you're chunking you're
thinking of three notes
as one thing one chord or one shape and
that has a massive impact with what
you're able to understand and do with
music get the foundation of those basic
positions as strong as you can to get
off to a good start
so i've mentioned a few times already
that you should pay attention to how
different musical elements are working
and how they're built that's the theory
side of things one of the things that's
going to allow you to do that
effectively is to think in terms of
numbers
for example if we take the c major scale
which i played earlier c to c we can
number the notes so starting on c one
two
three four five six seven and you can
say one again sometimes you can say
eight or octave if we play a g major
scale the same scale starting from the
note g
now g equals one so a equals two
three four five six seven and one again
each number one can be called the root
and that's where we start the scale and
when we say we're in the key of g for
example or the key of c that's what we
mean we're starting from that note
that's the number one knowing this means
that when you pay attention to a piece
of music you can say things like oh the
melody starts on the fifth note of the
scale for example so if we're in c the
fifth note would be g one two three four
five so the melody might just go like
downscale
and then you could recreate that same
thing in the key of g by playing the
same pattern from the fifth note of that
scale so in g the fifth note would be d
one two three four five
or in d
and f
and it sounds like the same thing now in
each key
so with that in mind we can also number
the notes of a chord so if i play that c
major chord again
there's three notes it's a triad
we have c
e
and g
so if c is one of this chord
the e would be three
one two three
and the g would be five one two three
four five now i know i'm skipping the
black notes but we number them in terms
of how many letters away they are so c
to e is three and c to g is five letters
away so for major chords then we have a
root a third and a fifth
if i play a g major chord the notes are
different g b d but we can still say
root third and fifth it's relative to
our new starting point g is the new
number one one more example if i play a
d major chord
d
f sharp and a
this is one of the reasons we have two
names for the black notes we want this
one to be a third so we call it f sharp
because d e f is three letters not g
flat because d e f g would be four
letters
sometimes we need to get a bit more
specific about the numbers so you need
to know about something called intervals
an interval is just the size of the gap
between two notes on the piano and we
can measure the size of the gap by how
many semitones or half steps away they
are so if i start from c
this note is one half step away two half
steps three
four five six and so on remember this
can look different on different parts of
the piano because the buttons or the
keys make an uneven shape so look at
this part and you can see it as being
more in a straight line so if i start
here and do the same thing this is one
semitone away two
three four five and so on so those size
gaps compared to the first example i did
are the same they just look different
and on the inside of a real piano they
would look like exactly the same size
now the important thing about these
different sized gaps is that each
different size has a unique color or
harmony or sound flavor however you
choose to think about it and really
that's where the music comes from it's
more about the relationships between the
notes than the notes themselves and how
far you move from one to another or how
they interact when you play them at the
same time these intervals are some of
the fundamental building blocks of music
each different sized interval has a
unique sound and a unique name and
sometimes more than one name too but
that needs its own separate video and a
lot of practice in order to completely
learn that so earlier on i played a c
major chord and told you that if you put
the middle note down it becomes a c
minor chord so what i've really done is
i've changed the size of that first gap
in the chord so it's a new interval so
it's a new flavor so the new chord is a
new combination of flavors so it creates
a completely new sound just like a good
chef needs to understand all of his
ingredients what each one tastes like
what goes with what as musicians we need
to understand intervals what each one
sounds like is called and how to find
them from any note on the piano remember
the shapes can look really different
depending on where you start so getting
used to that helps you move around the
keyboard much more easily every scale
and every chord is built with different
intervals so the easier you can
understand them and hear them and find
them on the piano the easier it's going
to be to understand chords and to be
able to expand your musical vocab but it
can also help you memorize patterns and
melodies on the keyboard because you can
see and hear it for example going up a
second and then down fourth up a third
it makes working music out by ear
writing music memorizing lots more music
much easier
following on from numbers and chords and
scales we actually have chords that fit
inside scales just worry about the major
scale to start with when something fits
inside a scale the word is diatonic
although the concept is more important
than remembering that word itself so
looking at the c major scale c to c
if we start a chord from the first note
of the scale
we can call that chord number one we
tend to use roman numerals in music for
this
uppercase for major and lowercase for
minor i'm playing our basic three note
chords triads for this example by
playing
every other note in the scale until i've
got three
so what i'm doing here really is i'm
stacking thirds here to here is a third
c d e it's three letters and here to
here is a third e f g is three letters
if i do the same thing from the second
note of the scale
i get chord number two
chord number three
four
five
six seven
and then we're back at one again
because every major scale is exactly the
same pattern of intervals just starting
from a different note that's why they
would have the same name absolutely
anything you do in one of those major
scales you can do exactly the same in
another one as long as it doesn't go out
of range of the keyboard so you have
those same seven chords that i just
played in all 12 keys and every time
each chord type is going to be the same
kind of chord so chord number one will
always be a major chord
chord number two
will always be a minor chord and the
reason that's gone to minor is because
the gap between these two notes see
there's two other notes in between them
is smaller than the gap between these
two notes there's three notes in between
them
so overall the seven diatonic chords the
chords of the major scale looks like
this
there's three major and there's three
minor number seven is a different type
of chord called diminished which is
basically the same as a minor chord
except the fifth has been shrunk or
flattened by one half step of course
chords can go out of the scale too but
you need to learn the ones that are in
the major scale first for a really
strong foundation of how this stuff
works so if i play a simple chord
progression c
g
a minor
f
those happen to be the famous iv chord
search that youtube and you'll see what
i mean we can say c g a minor f but it's
actually a bit more useful to think of
that progression as 1
4.
if i play that in the key of g for
example it's going to sound like the
same thing
obviously not exactly the same because
it's in a different range on the piano
but the pattern and the quality of it is
just the same
each chord in a key kind of has a unique
job and a unique sound an easy one to
get to grips with first is the number
one chord just like the number one note
it sounds finished and at home when you
land on that chord and you might often
end a song there for example other
chords can sound like they're building
up or some chords can sound like they're
pulling you back home it's called
functional harmony really but i just
think of it more as labeling things in a
way so you can get used to them and spot
the underlying things that link a lot of
music the more and more you get used to
it for example when the one chord goes
home or where it hangs on the v chord to
pull you to the chorus the more you
start hearing it everywhere and it
allows you to figure out chords to songs
quicker allows you to write chords but
also be able to memorize much more and
understand music with a much higher
proficiency at a much deeper level again
there's a lot more to it than that as
well and it takes a lot of experience
but if you start thinking like that
early on it's going to help you get
there much quicker
a big part of how music sounds is in
what the harmony is and what the chords
are you're playing but there's also a
lot of music in how you play those
chords we sometimes call that a chord
voicing there's actually a ton of
possibilities really as there's
potential to spread the different chord
tones out in any which way you like so
if there's three notes in the chord c e
and g
i've got c's e's and g's up and down the
entire piano so i could play a c here
the g there and the e here
and any other variation you could think
of so i could play them all up here down
here
and where and how you play them and how
spread the notes are how closed up the
notes are creates all these different
kinds of textures and effects eventually
you want to be able to see an entire
stream of a chord be able to jump to it
anywhere and recognize where music is
moving through it an experience will
teach you the kind of things that you
can do with it but learning the shapes
of chord inversions is the best and most
useful thing to do to set you off down
that path these are basically where you
rearrange the order of the notes or
invert the chord officially a chord
inversion should be where you change the
bass note because that has a big impact
on how you hear the other notes but
that's for another time really starting
out you can make a great deal of use out
of just the shapes themselves and use
them to get really familiar with the
keyboard and the different places you
can play the same chord using a mixture
of chord positions helps you control the
sound of the music much more you could
take something that might otherwise be a
bit plonky sounding and make the chords
move from one to the next in a much
nicer way this is called voice leading
just using our three note triads as an
example
as there's three notes there's three
different positions that you could play
the chord in and by that i mean three
positions where you get one of each note
in a row so not including spreading the
notes out all over the piano and this is
most useful because you can get a full
idea of what the chord sounds like by
getting one of each note in one hand
position that you can reach now of
course you can easily reach positions
where you have two of the same note but
it's much more useful in the long run to
get to grips with this first
so the starting position for a chord the
one you generally learn first is
actually called root position because it
begins from the root on the bottom
that's going from left to right so the
root's the number one in the chord so we
have the root the third and the fifth
if i take
this c and switch it for the next c up
i've still got the same three notes that
i started with c e g is now just e g c
well now it's third fifth and then the
root this is called first inversion it's
useful to always keep track of where the
root is so you remember what the name of
the chord is you're actually playing and
i like to think of this as the top down
shape get used to what the shape looks
like and feels under your fingers you've
got a bigger gap here and a smaller gap
here so this is a fourth and this is a
third remember that's just how many
letters away is one two three four one
two three
now if i take this low e
and switch it for the e above
i've still got the same three notes that
i started with originally so it's still
the same chord just in a different order
now i have fifth
root third
this one's called second inversion the
root's in the middle so i like to think
of this as the middle around shape
so get used to how this one looks and
feels under your fingers now you've got
that bigger gap of a fourth on the
bottom and a third on the top
so get used to all three shapes how they
look different this one's a more evenly
spread shape
this one's got the bigger gap on top
this one has the bigger gap underneath
for every chord you learn or just really
the triads at the moment you need to
learn every position that you can play
them i'll be doing a completely separate
video on how you can learn that really
well and practice it in different ways
so it becomes fluent but when you get
there it helps with so many aspects of
your playing you can understand what's
happening in the music at a much deeper
level you can recognize memorize and
hear parts of songs much more easily
using these shapes sometimes they're
played together as a chord or broken up
into a pattern or sometimes melodies
land on these notes and you can start
noticing that stuff much more easily
it's also going to help you technically
getting your fingers used to moulding
into different kinds of shapes if you're
playing a simple chord progression these
shapes will help you control the sound
and voice lead much better making your
playing sound far more musical
as a quick example of how you can
control the sound if i was just going
from c to g and only using root
positions it would sound like this
you may not always want that sound to
make such a leap so you could find a
closer position to go up to a g
you may also want the chord to sound
like it's moving down so you could go
from the same c
down to a g
if it's comfortable for you to see those
positions and find them easily then you
can make the music sound exactly how you
want if i play a whole chord progression
in root positions it might sound like
this
[Music]
with different inversions you can make
it move around much more smoothly like
this
that generally sounds smoother it may
not always be the best option but now
you have the control to do what the
music needs
lastly when you play a group of notes
together generally the top note is the
note that stands out to your ear the
most if you keep playing groups of notes
together one after the other the top
note can form a melody because that's
what stands out the most to your ear so
you can create melodies with how you
play chords
so i could bring out this melody with a
chord progression
or this melody
[Music]
using the same chords both times
or the other one
[Music]
i just changed the inversion so a
different note was on top and it draws
your ear to something else
so songs use these shapes all the time
and learning them really well can really
maximize how much you're able to learn
and memorize and how quickly and easily
you can do that and how much you can do
with chords
learn as much music as you can mainly
because that's the reason you're doing
this in the first place and everything
else i'm saying on this list is just to
make this part better but coming back to
language the first thing you do when
you're a kid is copy and mimic even
without any theory or exercises or
anything you can go a long way just
doing this and i'm going to say it's the
most important thing on this list
everything else is just to help you make
the most of your experience with songs
and music focus more on the music that
you're more passionate about but be
open-minded and learn a wide range of
music with that mentality you'll learn a
lot more about what you can do with the
piano don't try and play something
that's too far out of your reach at the
time you have to build up to stuff you
may need advice or a teacher to know
what that is but at the same time make
sure you're challenging yourself
sometimes technically or otherwise
that's a surefire way to make sure you
keep growing challenges can be learning
a new technique that you're used to more
complex chords more complex chord
progressions a new kind of rhythm
playing a song and a key that you're
less familiar with there's tons and try
to mix them up as much as possible
learning songs is satisfying you have
something to spur you on to want to
progress more you have something to show
for it and you can see how far you've
come you went from not being able to
play something to being able to play it
from there you can also use what you've
learned the song as a tool to improve on
things like your timing your sense of
rhythm dynamics your control and loads
of other stuff there's not just
different styles to think about but
different roles the piano has in
different situations so try and mix up
as much as you can what you're learning
you might be accompanying yourself or
another singer and have bass in the left
hand and chords in your right
[Music]
you might be playing in a band where you
don't always need to play bass notes you
might just be playing lead lines or a
riff
[Music]
the great thing about the piano is such
a versatile instrument and there's loads
of ways to use it and with enough
practice you can also be the whole band
play the bass the harmony and the melody
all at the same time
there's all kinds of possibilities to
keep your learning experience as varied
as you can play what you like mostly but
sometimes play things that you think may
help your progress and you'll find the
more that you learn the more your taste
expands anyway as much as you can at any
given time try and understand what's
happening in the music things like these
are the chords that i'm playing and this
is the key that i'm in that way you'll
maximize what you're getting out of
learning any song a bit of music
sometimes you might want to pick a song
to learn to focus on one specific like
technical skill for example and in that
case you might not want to think so much
about the theory otherwise it might get
a bit overwhelming and be
counterproductive but where you can
using the musical knowledge you have at
the time try and make as much sense of
it as possible
as a musician your ears are one of your
greatest assets music is sound at the
end of the day and there's lots of
things that you can be doing right now
to start developing a good ear and be
able to hear music in a different way
through years of teaching i have seen
that some people have a natural quicker
response to ear training than others but
really it's just something that
non-musicians aren't familiar with yet
and it's all completely trainable i
think some people are just a bit quicker
based on experience they've had in the
past even if it's just singing along to
the radio the first and most important
part i think is to listen to lots of
music again listen with an open mind and
to a wide variety of music and when i
say listen i mean really listen don't
listen passively with music just in the
background although obviously do that
for fun listen actively you won't be
able to pick out everything that's
happening obviously but just try to
start noticing as much as you can about
the musical language and absorb it you
don't have to get technical to start
with this part of the song sounds
lighter because he's played up high
this part sounds thicker and more
impactful because he's played some
deeper lower notes and thick chords
this part has some more unusual sounding
harmony which has created a weird effect
[Music]
here some chords are just being held to
ring out and now they're sounding short
and stabby and more of a rhythm and see
what impact that has on the feel this
song sounds bright and major this song
sounds dark and minor these are just
some examples of basic things that you
could be listening out for at this stage
don't just exclusively listen to piano
or keyboard parts either think about
what other musicians are doing too like
i said even without any theory
whatsoever there's so much that you can
try and be aware of and notice and
absorb to start speaking music each
different style of music has its own
accents and phrasing and ways of using
language and rhythm and note choices you
can learn so much just by listening
actively and getting used to those kind
of things you may not have the technical
facility or knowledge to actually be
able to recreate those sounds yet but
when you start learning that having the
sound of it in your head to start with
makes a huge difference when you come to
try and play it yourself someone could
probably make a good effort to describe
how a french accent sounds but you're
not going to be able to recreate it from
that you have to hear them speak and try
and mimic it yourself and all the little
things that make it sound like that also
listen to players that you like listen
to everything that they do the way they
play stuff their touch on the piano and
try and mimic that if that's how you
want to sound one day try and get used
to the sound of different types of
chords especially when you learn a new
one sometimes it's useful to describe to
yourself what the chord might sound like
or associate it with a piece of music
that you know that uses that chord for
example a major chord generally sounds
bright and happy
and a minor chord sounds darker and
sadder
[Music]
that one i played earlier
it's kind of a james bond sound although
in the context of an entire song a major
chord doesn't always sound happy it's
just an example another really
fundamental part of ear training that i
kind of mentioned earlier that all
musicians should be doing is to get
familiar with the sound of each interval
each different sized interval has its
own certain characteristic and there's
lots of methods you can use to get used
to them it takes a long time so it's one
of those things you build up slowly
again one common method is to associate
certain intervals with a piece of music
that you're really familiar with for
example this one
it's called a minor second it's the same
thing as a semitone or a half step and
that's the jaws thing
a fifth is part of the star wars theme
again i'm going to get into that deeper
in its own set of videos but it's
something that's really helpful to start
working on early on it takes lots of
practice to get quicker and quicker at
it but it can really help you with so
many things you can learn things by ear
much easier play what's in your head
memorize more music because you're able
to associate how it sounds with how to
play it you're making a stronger
connection between your inner ear and
your fingers once you start getting used
to how they sound to make that even
better you can start being able to sing
them being able to find them in your
head straight away but even before that
actually we should talk about pitching
so you don't have to be a great singer
but being able to pitch a note match
pitches is a really useful thing to try
and do even just matching notes on the
piano you might need someone who can
sing well to help you do that because
i've taught some people who can do it
instantly some people can't hear when
it's the same straight away but with
some practice they get used to
coming up or down to match the note and
then can start to hear when they're
doing the same thing having a strong
sense of sound and music and pitch in
your head to start with makes everything
else much easier and clearer and will
make you a better musician in the long
run beginners need to start trying to
work things out by ear even if that just
means falling around until it sounds
right that's all part of developing your
ear and you'll get more and more
familiar with hearing notes moving up or
down how far where they're moving in and
out of a scale if possible try to do it
knowing what scale it's in or even
better try and work out the scale but
even if you can't do that yet it's still
a really useful thing to start doing do
as much as you can you could do it using
famous melodies that you know really
well something that's just in your head
or on the radio often things like
nursery rhymes can be useful to start
with because they're relatively simple
and familiar but don't try and do some
crazy bebop line if you can't do bar bar
black sheep yet improvise a lot even if
it's just mucking about it doesn't have
to sound good yet pick a scale probably
just major scale first and try and come
up with your own melodies just noodle
about pay attention to where you are in
the scale and get used to what effect it
has when you leap a second a third or
fourth or fifth
listen to yourself whilst you play once
you have the mechanics of a sunk down so
you can play it without thinking quite
as hard this becomes much easier to do
listen for how you think the music
should sound try and listen as though
someone else is playing it and in your
head try and hear how you expect it to
sound that way you can start thinking a
bit more about the music subtleties the
dynamics and the timing that kind of
stuff and when you can control that more
it can start to sound a lot more
expressive and musical but it all starts
with how you hear it in your head
most music has some kind of rhythmic
backbone rhythm to put it in slightly
more boring terms is patterns of sound
or movement in relation to time i find
this one quite tricky to put into words
in a way that i'm happy with but it's
essentially the groove or the pulse of
the music players of all instruments use
rhythm but a more obvious example might
be a drummer or a percussionist not
always but in general we work against an
even grid of time and then divide that
grid up evenly in different ways and use
that to create patterns by hitting some
on the grid and leaving others out
giving some parts of its strong accents
and other parts weak accents but to be
honest i think the best approach to
learning a good sense of rhythm and
timing is just a natural one even just
listening to music and tapping along is
going to be useful you can start just by
listening to the drummer because it's
going to be easier to do it with first
and just by tapping along to the pulse
just make sure you can feel the hits of
your hands matching up with what you
hear then you can expand that and try
and match patterns they're doing try and
do your own patterns along with the good
thing about that kind of learning is you
can do it anywhere you're not having to
sit down and practice you just do it as
part of your everyday life and it helps
you get more absorbed in the musical
world it's more active listening like i
mentioned before we count rhythm in
repeated groups or bars or measures as
they say in the us the most common one
is groups of four so i'll use that as an
example like this
one two three four
one two three four one another common
one is three like a waltz kind of feel
one two three one two three one two
three one two three one if we have four
beats in a bar for example we can also
divide those beats and then with those
divisions we can create all sorts of
patterns by playing some of them not
playing some accenting some loudly
playing other ones softly there's loads
more you can do with this as well i'm
using drums as an example because i
think it demonstrates the point more
clearly there's also loads more stuff
you can do with rhythm but this is just
the basic principles when you're
listening and playing you want to focus
on developing a strong sense of even
time but not only that a strong sense of
feeling where the beat is the one the
two the three the four and what part of
the melody or anything else that you're
playing lands on the b or in and around
the b for example on an and so halfway
in between one strong b and the next so
for example if i play this melody
i could count that as one and two and
so i've started on a one
and then that next note's an and the
next note lands on the b two
and then it finishes on an end
and then the three comes afterwards one
and two
so some notes i'm hitting on the b and
other notes i'm hitting in between the b
and you want to try and develop a good
sense of focusing on where that strong
beat is one really common way to improve
your timing is to practice to a
metronome it improves how sensitive your
ears are to time but also how you can
control things in order to stay in time
pretty much all musicians i know do this
kind of practice a metronome is
basically a device that gives you evenly
timed clicks
to play along to whatever tempo you put
in tempo is just the speed of the music
and we measure it in bpm or beats per
minute the higher the bpm the faster the
tempo you can get old-fashioned
mechanical metronomes or more modern
digital ones but these days people tend
to use apps like this
some of your practice time with songs
should be to a metronome to help get
everything tighter metronomes are also
really useful for when you're doing
exercises like scales
[Music]
sometimes we might hold a note down for
four beats or two or one or half a beat
and we have different names for each of
those different note lengths you may
have heard these terms like eighth note
quarter note or in england we say like
crotchet and quaver that kind of thing
the theory side of notation can be
really useful to maximize how much you
can learn and understand this but it
also helps you communicate with other
musicians even if you don't learn to
read music you should learn the names of
those different note legs because it's
not really just a reading thing so as
you're listening remember to try and
listen actively and take note of what's
happening rhythmically in the music as
it's often an important signature to
make a certain style of music sound a
certain way for example reggae accents
beats two and four one two three four
one two three four one two three four
one two three four there's lots of
things to learn with rhythm but i think
the most important first steps is to
develop a good sense of where the pulse
is and how music dances around it again
there should be more lessons up soon to
help you develop this
following on from rhythm notation the
next thing on the list is learning how
to read music so this is one of those
things that depending on what musical
avenue you really want to go down can be
almost absolutely essential or something
you will never use i think for a lot of
people though it's somewhere in between
let me just quickly state the difference
between reading and sight reading
reading is basically being able to
figure out how to play something from
sheet music sight reading is being able
to do that instantly learning to read
fluently at a high level takes an
extremely long time years and years of
dedication on that particular skill it
can be really useful for professionals
in certain niches like the session
circuit musical theater and the
classical world but i just want to talk
about learning the basics and what that
can do for you now some people really
don't like reading music and despite
what some other people say it's not
absolutely essential for a lot of the
things that you do notation is not music
music is music if this list were in
order of importance it wouldn't be near
the top and personally i recommend
getting some basic experience actually
playing before you even start trying to
read people learn to speak before they
can read and write and i think that
pretty much sums up my opinion on the
matter but what it can do for you though
is open up new ways of learning it can
be easier to learn classical stuff like
this even if you don't just want to play
classical stuff it's nice to learn some
as you can learn a lot of new techniques
and understand more about what the piano
can do and how some of that filters into
more modern music it's sometimes just
easier to learn when you have the sheet
in front of you to remind you how to
play something that you can check
quickly learning by ear and memorizing
and from videos is great but sometimes
there's a better option notation can
also help you sometimes make sense of
what's happening in the music the chords
the harmony the rhythm for example
because you can see it on the page you
can write your ideas down too someone
can give you their ideas to play again
all this stuff is also doable without
notation but it can just be a really
handy thing to know so i at least
recommend learning the basics when you
do you'll be reading really slowly at
first how it works is actually fairly
uncomplicated but getting quick at it is
the bit that takes a long time to learn
even if you are figuring out things
slowly like i said it opens up a lot of
new possibilities of learning and that
can only really be a good thing and for
some people it might even be easier
this one's really important because it
affects everything else on the list
whether you're teaching yourself taking
lessons in person or online or learning
from a book most of the practice you'll
end up doing will be whilst you're on
your own you need to train yourself in
the most effective and efficient ways to
practice that you can and also learn
what the common pitfalls are to try and
avoid there's not time to go into all of
them here but i'll just name a few an
obvious one is to practice things slowly
gain the control and learn things
correctly and then speed will come a
slow pace allows more thinking time to
process what you're doing learn good
habits and build the correct muscle
memory isolate certain skills and give
yourself time to focus on that one
specific thing that may be a certain
technique a certain kind of chord or
even just one small section of a piece
of music that you're struggling to play
or memorize think clearly about whether
you're approaching the fingers in the
right way or your technique isn't
slipping a teacher is obviously really
useful in these kinds of situations but
if you're shrewd enough it's something
you can do by yourself and you should
still learn to do by yourself anyway
because like i said you'll be spending
most of the time practicing on your own
you've got to train yourself and get in
the habit of trying to notice these
things that you're doing or not doing to
maximize how much you progress you have
to learn to use your practice time
effectively so with each new skill you
learn find the best resource you can on
how to learn that particular thing so
you can make the best use of your
practice time it's my aim to make this
channel one of those resources but you
might be looking for something i haven't
covered so you need to build up your
list of good credible places that you
can go and look to for advice really
importantly you need to embrace the
learning process get used to a slow
repetitive process don't go in expecting
fast results ignore any video that's got
a title or anything like be a pro in
five minutes any half decent musician
will tell you that's the wrong attitude
to have to learning music things
sometimes have to be repeated hundreds
of times till it sticks that may be a
concept or perhaps something technical
sometimes you have to sit there for ages
playing the same thing but think of it
as an almost meditative process now i
completely understand that as a beginner
this can lead to some frustrating
moments because sometimes it just feels
hard like you won't be able to do it i
have been there all musicians have been
there you can't see the light at the end
of the tunnel at this stage but stick
with it because what happens is you get
used to and even start enjoying the
process because after a while you know
that when you're practicing something in
the right way you have the confidence
that you will achieve the result with
enough time and patience
if you haven't got the time for longer
practice sessions practice little and
often when you leave something a week or
two before you have another go you spend
half the next practice session trying to
get back to where you were before and
it's a waste of time i find the little
and often approach keeps things fresh in
your mind so that way when you go back
to it you're adding to it reinforcing
the information and not just going over
the same ground you're making the muscle
memory stronger you'll memorize things
better and it's less boring too you'll
see better results which is then more
motivating and then it just snowballs if
it's one technique or one small passage
or one exercise you're working on you
can do things like have a quick go
whilst you're waiting for the kettlebell
or before you leave the house quickly
there's loads of little ways that can
make the best use of your time do things
like that because it helps keep it fresh
and it doesn't even take up your normal
practice time either don't just keep
playing the bits that you know really
well and can do easily don't shy away
from the harder parts they're often the
bits that are going to lead you to grow
make sure you divide your practice time
up well get a good balance of learning
songs and exercises and the theory stuff
i would say the biggest chunk of time
should be spent learning songs and
actual music as that is why we're here
but remember the other things and
isolating specific elements and all that
kind of stuff can help you improve those
songs and grow quicker ultimately
helping you to make the most out of your
time actually playing music if you can
start trying to play music with other
people there's things you'll learn just
by doing that that you can never learn
in lessons in real life online or
practicing by yourself
just as one example you're forced to
listen more intensively because you have
to pay attention to what other people
are doing as well as yourself obviously
you might want to get some basic
facility on your instrument before you
start doing that but bear in mind
another really important one is to have
reasonable expectations about your
progress as i said at the beginning
music is something you learn slowly by
building up different skills and
knowledge don't expect to be oscar
peterson after a year embrace the
challenge the time the dedication it
requires and pretty obviously the more
time you put in as long as you learn to
use the time well of course the more
you're gonna get out of it so much of
what you learn isn't really rocket
science to get to grips with but it's
taking the time and the effort to get
fluent at it that's the hard work no
matter how good a teacher you have or
anything like that it's down to you to
keep practicing and practicing and
practicing until you can just do these
things by heart so really you want to be
learning stuff so well that you can
learn to forget it just like having an
everyday conversation in your native
language you don't have to think about
it you can just say what you want lastly
make sure to try and start seeing the
connections between the things that
you're learning you won't at first but
all this foundational stuff is part of a
much bigger picture and it takes a while
to get high enough to see the whole
thing don't forget to pay attention and
try and notice things you've learned in
music like a chord type in a song or a
riff that uses the blues scale or this
chord movement happens in these two
songs that i know it has a similar
effect in each this melody here is
landing on the notes of the chord that
i'm playing that kind of thing again
this is what adds to your musical
vocabulary so you can start speaking the
language
this has gone on for much longer than i
thought it would when i started this
video so i'll try and keep the last two
short and sweet there's lots of musical
lingo that musicians use the names of
chords scales words and directions for
how to play something words that i've
mentioned earlier like flat and sharp
and octave and tempo and keys
don't overwhelm yourself but as you go
pay attention as it can be extremely
useful to build this vocabulary up
especially if you're learning online
watching youtube or googling things
people will be using these words and
phrases all the time so to try and avoid
confusion when you discover something
new learn what it's called when you hear
a new word learn what it means sometimes
there's a few words that mean the same
thing which could be confusing so google
something if you're not sure what it
means and find out because you don't
want to learn the wrong thing by
accident there's also lots of latin
words and that kind of thing more in the
classical world and i wouldn't worry too
much about that unless you really want
to go down that avenue but some of those
are still common amongst all kinds of
music like legato and staccato i said
earlier smooth playing
and short and sharp playing like that
expanding this part of your musical
vocab is just going to make the learning
process that much easier and also help
you communicate with other musicians
about things
everything i've said so far sounds like
a lot of work and it kind of is but
remember these are things to be focusing
on over a long period of time and to be
honest some of these things you'll
always be working on to get better but
the whole point of everything i've
mentioned is to get you to a place where
you have more freedom with your playing
i promise the hard work on these kinds
of things makes the fun stuff a whole
lot more fun try to enjoy the learning
process along the way i know you'll have
moments of frustration where you feel
stuck but it's at these points that you
have to try and remember the most that
eventually you're going to enjoy the
fruits of your labor but even before
that the reason you clicked on this
video and the reason you decided you
wanted to learn an instrument is because
you enjoy music all of this stuff is
really craft but that craft allows you
to make music and art and be creative
use some of your practice time to fool
around be expressive discover new things
new sounds to be honest your passion for
music is going to take you further than
anything else on this list be excited to
learn new things experiment that's how
to stay motivated and improve
improvising is really fun because you
can let go a bit you can loosen up
physically and mentally and start to
think less about the craft and the
theory and just be musical you can pick
up things this way even if you don't
know what they mean different rhythms
touches on the keys interesting note
choices the theory can help you make
more sense of this stuff that you find
and memorize it better but you've got to
enjoy finding these things in the first
place so through things like improv and
just general experimentation and
creativity with the piano you can have
loads of fun with your playing and learn
so much and pick up so many things about
the musical language without even
realizing it
so like i said at the start these are
things to be worked on and built up over
a long period of time and the more
fluent you become the more you're going
to get out of it so don't feel defeated
if some things take a while to get or
come and go a little bit because that's
completely normal i'm going to be making
individual videos on each of these
topics which will be a lot more in depth
on how it works and how to learn it and
practice it and they'll be in the
description when they're up let me know
in the comments if this was helpful or
if there's anything else that you can
think of that beginners should be
working on thanks for watching please
like and subscribe if this video was
useful and see the next one
[Music]
you